[SPEAKER_02]: So, how do I take things that I know I should take seriously?
[SPEAKER_02]: How do I actually take them seriously when it comes down to it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Which is when usually it's not a big deal.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you have to start making an effort way before it comes down to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you have reasons to take something seriously, when you then need to apply diligence before, as I said,
[SPEAKER_01]: Those serious choices present themselves.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, start actually, yeah, reflecting, not forgetting, and building up determination that when those choices present themselves, you don't choose wrongly.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you just think that deciding to choose rightly, when the time is right, and then not doing anything in the meantime, in terms of saying little no's to yourself, saying... containing the mind to the best of your abilities, bit by bit, if none of that's done, when the time comes, the mind will choose what the... where the floodgates go, basically open and go.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there will be no means of saying no to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Determination will just be
[SPEAKER_01]: Any determination you made beforehand will just be insignificant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need to build it up and work on it before that full-on pressure is felt to go towards sensuality or ill-will or bad habits and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, how would you know if you're being a bit too specific with, like, you know, obviously, if you get way too into kind of this one thing that I think is unwholesome,
[SPEAKER_02]: What do you mean?
[SPEAKER_02]: Can you be more specific?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, say you... say you're kind of caught up with, like, oh, this specific activity is a problem, versus a more... and you kind of make that the focus, you might be... Well, if, presumably, you mean to train in the precepts, so then any activity that's... that's pushing you or bringing you closer to breaking the precepts, to compromising the foundation of the training, well, that's the activity that must be restrained and abandoned.
[SPEAKER_01]: If then you start picking on other random activities for whatever, you know, you might not be very clear about it, you just have a need to say no to more stuff, then, yeah, you could maybe reflect on that and check, because you might not be necessary to say no to everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, because, you know, once you start saying no to right things, the momentum of that will want to make you start saying no to everything, because the more, the better.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how it feels.
[SPEAKER_01]: The natural, you know, how the suttas describe, like, people first live completely oblivious, engaging with sensuality left and right, then they kind of hear about it, discern some value of saying no to it, but now they want to say no to everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, they'll stop eating, they'll stop sleeping, they'll stop this, they'll stop talking, they'll stop everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, well, that becomes equally ignorant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in order to reach, well, in order to discern that balance, yeah, first you have to say no to the obvious coarse sensual cravings.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, when the tendency to kind of turn towards asceticism or saying no to even activities that are neutral, when that comes up, well, you got to recognize that and maybe say no to that need.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how you stay in the middle between the two.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can't
[SPEAKER_01]: Discern the middle of the bat.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you can't immediately start in a perfect tune.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to be like tightening, loosening, tightening, loosening, until you discern what's neither too tight nor too loose.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, trial and error is kind of inevitable to some extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, the clearer you are, in terms of, you know, the preset, the purpose of the training, the characteristics that need to be discerned, you know, in phenomena, as the suttas talk about, more accurate your trial and error will be.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's still gonna be kind of, you know, too tight, too loose, too tight, too loose, until the right tune is recognized and played.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm wondering if the way that the suttas, when they talk about sensuality, they kind of divvy it up into, you know, like speaking about it in terms of the five senses, and it gives the impression that it's always just like focused on one.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, I really want to taste this, or I really want to see this.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it seems like it's often a bit more nuanced than that, and that your reasons for engaging in sensuality might be
[SPEAKER_02]: Something more inclusive?
[SPEAKER_02]: I'll give a concrete example.
[SPEAKER_02]: Some people say that they would have no problem abstaining from sexuality just on a physical basis.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then, it's actually the thought of the implications about not having a partner, not being loved, not having kind of that reciprocal relationship.
[SPEAKER_02]: That is the point where they actually start to get uncomfortable.
[SPEAKER_02]: The thought of just physically abstaining doesn't present that.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, that dimension of sexuality is not...
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not about, like, the coarse physical sensations, but that doesn't mean it's not sensual.
[SPEAKER_01]: So... Well, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It can... it can take myriad of forms, depending on the person.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even as the sutta says, oh, man tastes vary.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, so, somebody can be into this, into that, somebody can prefer this aspect or that aspect.
[SPEAKER_01]: The bottom line is, if you find what your mind sensually craves,
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, for some people it would be very coarse, for some people not so coarse forms of it, but it's still going to be the same root of the same craving, same type of craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you start... if a person recognizes that, and then recognizes that kind of, as I said, mental dependence on those things, like, oh, you know, I have no problem giving this up, but if I need to give that up,
[SPEAKER_01]: That fills the mind with fear or, you know, as the suttas describe, it feels like an abyss, like a sudden precipice, like, I can't do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you realize, oh, well, that's where the work is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the mind has to get used to that and see why.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, like, any attachment is a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: Any attachment is an obstruction, which means any aspect of sensuality will be an obstruction.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're like, oh, it's not as coarse, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: But for you, that is the current thing that obstructs the mind from development.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, the suttas speak about it left and right, constantly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even when the, you know, you sometimes had people say like, oh, well, no, this is just a minor thing, minor sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: In that āgama, there was, what Ajahn Chah brought up, there was that monk that was associating with the nuns, enjoying their company, not doing anything, not breaking the rules, you know, technically.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, eh... the word got on to the Buddha, and then he said, oh, well, that's not a big deal.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, this doesn't need to be confessed.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not, you know, I'm not to engage in sexual...
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not even having sexual thoughts, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's more like just company, just friendship, or whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the Buddha told him off.
[SPEAKER_01]: He said, you know, man, when did you hear me saying that any aspect of sensuality is not an obstacle?
[SPEAKER_01]: Where did I say that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Didn't I, on so many occasions, talk about sensuality and giving similes of a burning pit, the bone, the chopping block, and so on?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, like, you can't compare with others.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, look, this person's fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: It depends what your intention is, depends what state of your mind is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why, like, some people would feel like, oh, it's too much to give this up in regard to the physical aspect.
[SPEAKER_01]: Some people wouldn't have problem giving it up, but they would have problem giving up the mental aspects of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you realize, well, like, you know, sure, I can technically find a way around this and say, well, look, the precepts doesn't say this.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, you know, if I'm honest with myself, and see where my intention is rooted, and that it feels like an abyss, because the untrained mind doesn't want to go there, well, that is the dhamma, that is the training.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because when the Buddha taught the dhamma, there were no rules for the first who knows how many years, literally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Monks didn't have any rules.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because everybody who understood the intention of dhamma, understood what intentions contradicted.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the first rules were formed.
[SPEAKER_01]: And actually, when they asked the Buddha to form the rules, preemptively, he said that's impossible for the Tathāgata to preemptively address things that haven't occurred or happened.
[SPEAKER_01]: The dhamma is the guide in and of itself for those who see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know exactly what's obstructing it, and you know exactly what isn't obstructing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, the rules were formed later on, when basically, the whole kind of direct contact and recognition of the principles of the dhamma were becoming obscured, through sheer kind of loss of quality of people admitted and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's inevitable.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in this case, it's the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you could say, well, look, friendship or relationship, it's not against the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: I keep the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: We both keep the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: We're both celibate or
[SPEAKER_01]: To the best of our ability and so on, it's like, okay, but if you are the one who wants to practice for, like, liberation from suffering... By the way, if that person is not interested in that, then none of this applies, as it goes without saying.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if a person is interested, then it doesn't really matter if there is a specified rule against it or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: What matters is, is this coming out of attachment or craving?
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, the answer is evident and obvious to anybody honest enough to admit it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what becomes the criteria.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, well, it's not a problem, but it is a problem for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, for whatever reason, and I don't need to psychologize to find out why my mind really wants this and fears giving it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's enough that I see that it is so.
[SPEAKER_01]: And which means, okay, so now we have to train you in contemplating losing those things, giving those things up until you calm down.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you might realize, oh, yeah, I never really wanted it that much.
[SPEAKER_01]: I never really cared about it that much.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it wasn't about you.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was about training that animal that, for whatever reason, wants this, doesn't want that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you know, it's not going to be pleasant working through that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's it's the only way, because pretty much, like, your attachments tell you where the direction of the practice is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whether there is a rule of that is an instruction, whether some teacher told you about it or not, again, if you understood the principle of training correctly, principle of taming, you don't need any more instruction.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's exactly what the Buddha said to some monks and nuns.
[SPEAKER_01]: He says, whatever, whatever leads to lust,
[SPEAKER_01]: Away from non-lust, that's not the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever leads away from lust, that's the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever leads towards hatred, delusion, whatever leads away from it, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And laid out is like, I don't know, a dozen or so standards, which anybody, at any point, in any culture, in any future, can use to discern what's in line with the dhamma and what isn't in line with the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that removes all the loopholes, all the technicalities, all the things that were not stated in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's all gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the principle is stated, and it's all inclusive.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like how the Buddha gave the simile, like an elephant footprint includes all the other smaller footprints in itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the point.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because sooner or later, a person will come.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everybody will come at that kind of... like a crossroad, in a way.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, oh, yeah, you know, I'm keeping the precepts, but there are certain things that are not against the precepts, but I do repeatedly see, recognize, and...
[SPEAKER_01]: Discern that the mind, for whatever reason, really depends on this, really wants it, really protects it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's really attached to it, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: But because it's not against the precepts, it's not against the training, I won't deal with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll deal with these other secondary things.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like... you'll only go so far with that type of attitude.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to recognize it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you're not gonna... you're not gonna fix the attachments overnight.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not gonna be enough to just, oh, say no to this and never again.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you can try.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the point is, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: I need to, like, train the mind away from these things.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can't just say no, and dismiss everything, and make these blind uttanga and determinations, and just stick through it, power through.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, no, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind, for whatever reason, like an example you gave, values, wants, needs relationships.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I recognize that as an objective phenomenon, as a fact.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can't just...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, I can say no, but again, the animal will still want it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, I need to contemplate and make, as I said, the diligent effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: First, not blindly pursuing the relationships, and then contemplating the danger, the weight, the burden,
[SPEAKER_01]: The implications of it, repeatedly, until the mind's like, oh yeah, you're right.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, it will forget the next day.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, I have to do it again, and again.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how you train the mind away.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's like, again, the suttas describe that, just in broad terms, as the suttas are very broad.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like bringing up certain perceptions of impermanence, of loss, of decay, of so...
[SPEAKER_01]: That pretty much, again, as I said, encompass anything you might be attached to or interested in.
[SPEAKER_01]: It undermines it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're not just bringing up a perception of impermanence in a theoretical, abstract manner.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ah, anicca.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you're finding what the mind depends on, and then you are undermining it by a gradual, controlled perception of impermanence of those things while the mind wants them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that the mind stops wanting them.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so that you can actually... so that both of you, you and your mind, can experience unshakable peace.